Guide to the Rainbow Alliance Records, 1987-2015 UA.55.16.13
ULS Archives & Special Collections
Rainbow Alliance Records
1987-2015
ULS Archives & Special Collections
Rainbow Alliance
UA.55.16.13
2.5 Linear Feet (4 boxes)
Rainbow Alliance is a student organization at the University of Pittsburgh that focuses on queer issues on campus. The records document the progress of the organization's early activist work from when they were known as BiGALA (Bisexual, Gay, and Lesbian Alliance) to the more social organization of Rainbow Alliance from 1987 to 2015. Published opinion pieces on LGBTQIA+ topics, marches/protests, social club gatherings, and public club sponsored events are evident within the documents contained in the records.
History
The organization known as the Rainbow Alliance has been active since 1972, originating under the initial title of "Gay Students at Pitt" as an informal student group. Their name changed to "Gay Pitt Supporters" in 1976 when they became recognized as an official student organization by the University of Pittsburgh and were allocated funding from Pitt's Student Government Board. In 1980 the group went by GALA (Gay and Lesbian Alliance) and then BiGALA (Bisexual, Gay, and Lesbian Alliance) in 1990, to be more inclusive of bisexuals. The organization's name was changed to Rainbow Alliance in 1997.
BiGALA was a political and social activist group whose goal was to create a more tolerant campus for people of all sexual orientations and to create a space of acceptance for gay students. This was achieved primarily through activist work and secondarily through social events. Prominent activties included educating people on issues like AIDS, safe sex, and sexual orientation. Public figures were often brought to campus to deliver speeches in attempt to educate the student body and faculty on subjects relating to homosexuality.
Since 1997, the Rainbow Alliance has continued much of the same activist work as its predecessors. Education on AIDS and safe sex persisted, in addition to documenting the legal battle for same-sex benefits at the University of Pittsburgh. The organization has filed several complaints against the University for discrimination based on gender identity and sexuality. Workshops have expanded from safe sex to include gender, race, and other topics relating to the LGBTQIA+ community. Political figures, queer activists, media stars, and pop culture icons are often brought to campus to deliver speeches or put on interactive and educational events to draw in a larger number of students from outside the organization. Social events for both members and non-members of Rainbow Alliance have become a prominent feature of the organization. Events include movie nights, social hours, dances, and the creation and continuation of Rainbow Alliance's yearly Drag Show. Club-sponsored events have primarily been hosted in the William Pitt Union, O'Hara Student Center, and the Cathedral of Learning.
Scope and Content Notes
The records include photographs, flyers, magazine and newspaper articles, and digital media that document events sponsored by Rainbow Alliance and its predecessors. Newspapers, newspaper clippings, and a scrapbook contain published articles relating to the LGBTQIA+ community in Pittsburgh, the organization's activist efforts, and club-sponsored events. Also included in the records are awards received by the club.
Access Restrictions
A piece of correspondence housed in Box 1 Folder 5 is closed until 2059. A redacted copy is available in Box 1 Folder 4 for research use.
Acqusition Information
Gift of Rainbow Alliance on October 2015.
Arrangement
The Rainbow Alliance Records are arranged into seven series:
Series I: Awards
Series II: Correspondence
Series III: Domestic Partner Benefits Issue at Pitt
Series IV: Flyers and Handbills
Series V. Newspaper Clippings and Articles
Series VI. Digital Media
Series VII. Photographic Material
Related Material
Pittsburgh International Lesbian and Gay Film Festival Records, 1983-1994, CTC.1994.02, Curtis Theatre Collection, Archives & Special Collections, University of Pittsburgh Library System.
University of Pittsburgh Women's Studies Program Records, 1970-2005, UA.15.26, University Archives, Archives & Special Collections, University of Pittsburgh Library System.
Domestic partner benefits; Student movements -- Pennsylvania; University of Pittsburgh; Gays -- Social life and customs; Pittsburgh (Pa.); Gay college students; Sexual minorities; Same-sex marriage -- United States; College Students -- Political activity; National Rainbow Coalition (U.S.)
- Awards, 2008-2011; I.
  Scope and Content Notes
  This series contains awards bestowed upon Rainbow Alliance by other student organizations, Pitt News, and the University of Pittsburgh's Office of Cross Cultural and Leadership development.
  - Office of Cultural and Leadership Development, 2008 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Best Student Advocacy Group, 2010 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Pitt News Best Student Organization, 2011 (Box 1, Folder 3)
- Correspondence, 2009; II.
  The Correspondence series contains a redacted copy of a letter written to the organization from a gay-identifying University of Pittsburgh alumnus. The original letter is included in the series, but access is restricted due to privacy concerns.
  - Transcription of Letter from Pitt Alumnus, 2009 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Original Letter from Pitt Alumnus [CLOSED--NO ACCESS UNITL 2059], 2009 (Box 1, Folder 5)
- Domestic Partner Benefits Issue at Pitt, 1993-2006; III.
  The Domestic Partner Benefits series contains news stories relating to the legal issue of domestic partner benefits. There is a primary focus on media coverage and opinion pieces on the Henson v. University of Pittsburgh legal case. Rainbow Alliance ran a webpage titled Pitt Discriminates, documenting the Henson case and media articles discussing same-sex benefits that has since been taken down from the internet. This series includes most of the printed digital publications and pertinent legal information on domestic partner benefits, like affidavits, that were linked to the Pitt Discriminates website. This information was collected by Rainbow Alliance as a part of the campaign to get the University of Pittsburgh to approve domestic partner benefits for university employees.
  - Henson v. University of Pittsburgh, ACLU Facts, 1999-2002 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Henson Case, Media Coverage, 1999-2000 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Editorials, Columnist and Letters to the Editor, 1999-2000 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Editorials, Pitt Faculty, Staff and Student Responses, 1999-2000 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Editorials, Community and Administration Responses, 1999-2000 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Hunger Strike, 1999 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Equal Rights Alliance, Media Releases, 1999-2000 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Correspondence, Pitt Administration, 1999-2004 (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Carnegie Mellon and Pennsylvania State University, Same-Sex Benefits Media Coverage, 1993-2000 (Box 1, Folder 14-15)
  - Pittsburgh Post-Gazette, Articles, 1999-2002 (Box 1, Folder 16-17)
  - Pitt News, Articles, 2001-2002 (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - Media Coverage, Activism and Same-Sex Benefits Controversy, 1999-2000 (Box 1, Folder 19)
  - University Times and Pittsburgh Tribune-Review Articles, 1996-2004 (Box 1, Folder 20)
  - Pitt's Compromise and Committee Formation, 1999-2002 (Box 1, Folder 21)
  - Pitt's Arguments Against Same-Sex Benefits Refuted, 1999-2000 (Box 1, Folder 22)
  - Employers that Provide Domestic Partner Benefits, 1999-2002 (Box 2, Folder 1-2)
  - Company Policies and Procedures on Domestic Partner Benefits, 1993-2001 (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - University Policies and Procedures on Domestic Partner Benefits, 1993-2006 (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Cost and Reports on Domestic Partner Benefits, 1993-2002 (Box 2, Folder 5)
- Flyers and Handbills, 1988-2012; IV.
  This series includes flyers that advertise events hosted and sponsored by Rainbow Alliance and its predeessors. Events featured on the advertisements include social gatherings, political discussions, and guest speakers visiting campus in addition to club informational flyers.
  - Events, 1988-2007 (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - Events, 2008-2010 (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - Events, 2011 (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - Events, 2012-2013 (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - Events, 2014-2015 (Box 2, Folder 10)
  - Event Posters (Oversized), 2010-2012 (Oversize 3, Folder 1)
  - Club Informational Flyers, undated (Box 2, Folder 11)
- Newspaper Clippings and Articles, 1987-2015; V.
  This series includes newspaper articles related to the LGBTQIA+ community with a primary focus on issues occurring in Pittsburgh, Pennsylvania, and the University of Pittsburgh Oakland campus.
  Melissa Smith was co-president of Rainbow Alliance from 1990-1992. Smith was an openly bisexual woman and was frequently featured in Pitt News articles discussing club sponsored events, advocating for gay rights and representation, and highlighting the importance of having a gay organization such as BiGALA on campus. Smith was appointed to a position on Pitt's Student Government Board in January 1992, resulting in her resignation as co-president of BiGALA. However, Smith felt like her voice was not being recognized by the other Student Government Board members and she resigned in September that same year.
  - Loose Clippings, 1989-1998 (Box 2, Folder 12)
  - Loose Clippings, 2007-2008 (Box 2, Folder 13)
  - Loose Clippings, 2009-2011 (Box 2, Folder 14)
  - Loose Clippings, 2011-2015 (Box 2, Folder 15)
  - Mounted Clippings, BiGALA, 1990-1993 (Box 2, Folder 16)
  - Mounted Clippings, Rainbow Alliance, 1997-2012 (Box 2, Folder 17)
  - Mounted Clippings, Pitt, 1991-2013 (Box 4, Folder 1-2)
  - Mounted Clippings, City of Pittsburgh, 1992-2012 (Box 4, Folder 3)
  - Mounted Clippings, National/Non-Specific, 1992-2012 (Box 4, Folder 4)
  - Pitt News, Articles (Oversized), 2008-2014 (Oversize 3, Folder 2)
  - Pitt News (Oversized), September 2, 2004 (Oversize 3, Folder 3)
  - Pitt News (Oversized), 2012-2014 (Oversize 3, Folder 4)
  - Pitt News (Oversized), 2014-2015 (Oversize 3, Folder 5)
  - University Times (Oversized), September 2, 2004 (Oversize 3, Folder 6)
  - New York Times (Oversized), March 27, 2013- March 28, 2013 (Oversize 3, Folder 7)
  - Pittsburgh Post-Gazette Articles (Oversized), October 19, 2014 (Oversize 3, Folder 8)
  - Scrapbook, 1987-1993 (Oversize 3, Volume 1)
- Digital Media, 2003-2010; VI.
  The Digital Media series consists of born digital records stored on CDs, CD-Rs, and DVDs. The records relate to events sponsored, hosted, or involved with the Rainbow Alliance.
  - "Rainbow Alliance" (CD-R), 2003 (Box 4, Folder 5)
  - "Day of Silence and Drag Show" (CD), 2006 (Box 4, Folder 6)
  - "Fashion Show"(DVD+R), 2007 (Box 4, Folder 7)
  - "Drag Show" (CD-R), 2007 (Box 4, Folder 8)
  - "Drag Show" (CD-R), 2008 (Box 4, Folder 9)
  - "Pride Week" (CD-R), 2010 (Box 4, Folder 10)
- Photographic Material, 1991-2010; VII.
  This series includes images of Rainbow Alliance and BiGALA members, public figures, and various events relating to the organization such as the annual drag show, National Coming Out Week, and a club dance.
  - Hillman Library Exhibit, 1991 (Box 4, Folder 11)
  - Dance, 2004 (Box 4, Folder 12)
  - Drag Show, 2006 (Box 4, Folder 13)
  - Vagina Monologues Performance (?), 2007 (Box 4, Folder 14)
  - National Coming Out Week, 2007 (Box 4, Folder 15)
  - Don't Ask Don't Tell Protest, 2010 (Box 4, Folder 16)
  - Meghan McCain Visits Pitt, 2010 (Box 4, Folder 17)
  - Public Figures, undated (Box 4, Folder 18)
  - Unidentified Events, undated (Box 4, Folder 19)